Guide to the Amos Alonzo Stagg Papers 1866-1964
University of Chicago Library
- Series VIII: Scrapbooks, Notebooks, and Albums
  - Subseries 1: University of Chicago Athletic Scrapbooks
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.91, December 1910-february, 1911 - Includes hunting deaths equal to the number of football deaths, varsity football, track, basketball, crew at the University of Minnesota, hockey, baseball, demands for a new stadium and athletic buildings to be built, Michigan and the Big Eight, amateurism ideals, possible Japanese baseball trip to the United States, a breakdown of athletic receipts (by sport) for Purdue University, swimming, high school athletics, possible game with the Cubs, and plans for the Olympics. Also contains birth announcements, University of Chicago magazine coverage on the football dinner given by the alumni, wedding announcements, programs for the athletic carnival, track and field, and the indoor meet and dance for the Irish-American Athletic Club. (Box 172)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.92, February-March, 1911 - Includes varsity track, changes and modifications of football, American Olympic team to be formed, baseball, swimming, track meet rules, golf and the Western Intercollegiate Golf Association, the formation of the College Athletic Conference of the Middle West (consists of Beloit, Lake Forest, Knox, Monmouth, and the Armor Institute), the question of summer baseball, basketball, and a outline of the Olympic program for Stockholm, Sweden. Also contains birth announcements, indoor athletics schedule (swimming, track, and basketball), programs for dual track and swim meets, telegrams, and track programs for Cook County high schools. (Box 173)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.93, March-April, 1911 - Includes White Sox baseball, Japanese University to play Chicago, the Cubs, and other universities, fencing, track, Cook County Athletic League track championships and programs, basketball, swimming, baseball, wrestling, Michigan and the Big Eight, and a British Scientist studies cleanliness and finds that bathing, too much air and exercise can be problematic for athletes. Also contains a “to do” list for filling out outcome of Intercollegiate Conference Meet, typed results of 1st, 2nd, 3rd, and 4th annual Intercollegiate Conference Meet, yells and cheers, invitation and menu for the congratulatory dinner for George E. Vincent’s presidency of the University of Minnesota, track swim meet programs, and a program for the Western Intercollegiate Gymnastic Championship Meet (also has wrestling and fencing as events). (Box 173)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.94, April-May, 1911 - Includes varsity track, baseball, Waseda University of Japan v. Chicago in baseball, “The Law of the Track” by Mike Murphy, Chicago students learn Japanese yells, baseball as seen by the Japanese, crew at eastern universities, Illinois and Purdue days, tennis, Joseph E. Raycroft to be Princeton’s athletic director, and letter from Chicago Alumni Club about annual dinner and election of officers. Also contains wedding invitations, baseball and track schedules and scorecards, announcements and scorecards for Waseda baseball game, flyer for Illinois Day, and programs for Interscholastic high school track, Wisconsin v. Illinois in track, Pennsylvania relay races, and Purdue day. (Box 174)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.95, June-September, 1911 - Includes the twentieth anniversary celebration for the University of Chicago, baseball, track, Olympic rules and American team members, Waseda University ball games, conference track meets, high school track meets and programs, Women’s Athletic Association opens its June Festival with a dance, tennis, interscholastic meets and programs, article on how to exercise properly, home-coming RSVP slips, coverage and programs for Chicago men (including living graduates, alumni and students), football, and physical education becomes a “major” at Wisconsin. Also contains wedding invitations, programs and invitations for the Women’s Athletic Association banquet and awards ceremony, entertainment programs for interscholastic meet, Order of the “C” banquet menu, souvenir programs and scorecard of the Waseda v. Chicago game, program and advertisement of for the 3rd Annual Athletic Festival (including May Pole dancing, the Sword Dance of Japan, relays, baseball, and parades), a handwritten speech and song for 1911 WAA banquet, songs and yells, programs for Yale-Harvard v. Oxford-Cambridge at the Queen’s Club in London (includes track and the report of the graduate finance committee) and the All-Around Championships of the United States, birth announcements, handwritten notes on a baseball game, preliminary plans for Alumni Reunion for Home-Coming, and a Presidential Invitation for Mr. And Mrs. Stagg to dine at the White House. (Box 174)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.96, September-October, 1911 - Includes varsity football, players and coaches, changes in rules, soccer, the “Marquis of Queensberry” favors University of Illinois football, Chicago students earn money to pay for school, high school football, birth announcements, Collier’s Outdoor America and the “New Football” by Caspar Whitney, and an invitation, program and response card for the inauguration of George E. Vincent as president of Minnesota. (Box 175)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.97, October-November, 1911 - Includes varsity football, athletics at the University of Wisconsin, soccer, plans for 1912 Olympic squad, football at the University of Minnesota, “muscular women athletes condemned and certain sports are bad for women” (includes basketball, hockey, swimming, and dancing), Wisconsin Athletic Bulletin, Chicago yells and cheers, and telegrams. (Box 175)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.98, November, 1911 - Includes football, professionalism accusations, Minnesota and problems with the Big Eight, football at Cook County high schools, Olympic trial to be held at Chicago campus, Olympic rules, German gymnasium and athletic societies, “State’s Restaurant” songs and menus, ”The March of the Maroons” song, and an article by James Sullivan on Athletic Growth and the popularity of athletics in America. (Box 176)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.99, November-December, 1911 - Includes football, players and coaches, problems with Minnesota and Wisconsin, corrupt football, amateurism v. professionalism, cross country running, summer baseball and the Big Eight, Olympic rules, Western Conference Championship left undecided, more demands for changing football rules, rugby, basketball, and changes in track rules. Also includes “algebraic athletics,” alumni announcements for annual football dinner, “Saturday Evening Grin” satirical paper with songs, cheers and jokes, the Yearly Buffoon, Minnesota Alumni Weekly Magazine, photo of the “champions” of Agricultural College in New Mexico, and a birth announcement. (Box 176)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.100, December, 1911-January, 1912 - Includes Olympic trials, dates and American team, Walter Camp’s All-Americans, football, using the forward pass, basketball, summer baseball debate, varsity golf, tennis, track, swimming, and the possibility of an Olympic stadium for Chicago campaign for 1916 Olympic. Also contains professionalism v. amateurism, water polo rules reforms, Walter Camp’s twenty greatest football celebrities, card for Caspar Whitney, Order of the Skull and Crescent Banquet program in honor of the all-star high school football team, wedding announcements, telegrams, and a flyer for basketball game. (Box 177)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.101, January-March, 1912 - Includes Big Eight conference problems, controversy over summer baseball, varsity track, football and the forward pass, varsity basketball, swimming, Stagg and student morale, gymnastics, baseball, high school athletics, wrestling, fencing, Olympic trials in Chicago, intramurals favor abandoning varsity sports, and amateurism in athletics. Also contains a diagram of football rules, golfing at Pinehurst in North Carolina, track and swimming programs, and a wedding invitation. (Box 177)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.102, April-June, 1912 - Covers varsity baseball, track, professional athletic directors and the Big Eight board, Ohio State and the Big Nine, “Football during Shakespeare’s life,” and Rockefeller donates money to send athletes to Olympics in Sweden. Gymnastics, problems with the Big Nine, and James Lightbody of Chicago attempts to rouse interest in athletics in Germany. Amateurism and eligibility, varsity letter for fencing, College of Hawaii plays Chicago in baseball, “the fable of Pete and Jack” a story about amateurism and summer baseball, Olympic trials, tennis, and the Western Conference meet. Also contains programs for the Spring Athletic Festival, track, and Middle West Conference Physical Education and Hygiene demonstration (includes fencing, baseball, marching, and dancing), flyers for Olympic tryouts for decathlon, invitations to Chicago Alumni dinner, birth announcements, and a program for first annual open indoor athletic meet for Omaha Young Men’s Christian Association. (Box 178)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.103, December, 1911-June 1912 - Includes controversy over summer baseball, Purdue’s Athletic Association Treasurer’s Report (broken down by sport), resolutions on summer baseball, student’s want to drop out of Big Nine conference, amateurism v. professionalism, student candidates for Minnesota and Indiana athletic board of control, Indiana football, game dates, Indiana and Purdue basketball, physical education, track, high school state championships in track, interscholastic track and tennis, Olympic tryouts, and athletes chosen to represent America in Stockholm Olympic games. (Box 178)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.104, June-July, 1912 - Interscholastic high school track, Everett C. Brown raises money for 1912 Olympians, Stagg gets honorary degree from Springfield YMCA College, summer coaching course offered at the University of Chicago, student signs to play baseball with the Philadelphia “Phillies,” Olympic trials and team members, history of the games. Includes 1912 Olympics in Stockholm, schedule of events, Swedish royalty preside over ceremonies and distribute prizes, Sweden considered a “good host,” men’s and women’s gymnastic displays, and coverage on Stockholm. Chicago athletes participating in the games, difficulties in training, and Swedish women as athletes. Also contains baseball and track schedules, letter to the “C” men to help send “Jimmie” to the Olympics, songs for Chicago Alumni Club, programs of entertainment for interscholastic meets, wedding invitations, and birth announcements. (Box 179)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.105, July-October, 1912 - Men’s and women’s tennis and club, new coach for Wisconsin, “nerve and grit” responsible for American Success at Olympics, games lead to improved relations between Sweden and the United States, Olympic parades and ceremonies revisited, and J.E. Raycroft establishes a department of hygiene and physical involvement at Princeton. Also contains physical education in Great Britain, Sir Arthur Conan Doyle an advocate of sports, A.G. Spalding claims baseball key to American success, swimmer discusses the games, relations between British and American athletes. Football, predictions for the season, Marshall Field stadium under repairs, Big Nine coaches, and the new football rules explained. Also contains wedding invitations and birth announcements. (Box 179)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.106, October-November, 1912 - Includes football, team members, the season planned for the Big Nine, preparations and results of games, Stagg develops new plays for Wisconsin game, enlists former Maroon stars to advise and coach for big game with University of Wisconsin, telegrams, cards with “Remember 1911” and a cartoon of a badger, wedding invitations, and menus for the Chicago-Wisconsin football banquet and the dinning car of the Illinois Central Railroad with the “Maroon Special.” (Box 180)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.107, November, 1912 - Football, preparations and results for Big Nine games, University of Chicago wins state title in football, lectures given on athletics, cross-country running, and Catholic institutions to form their own athletic conference (Notre Dame, Loyola, Marquette, St. Louis, and St. Viatos). Also contains basketball, 1912 football schedule, newspaper photo of 1912 Illinois team, the Yearly Buffoon (satirical University of Chicago newspaper), and a card advertising the “famous moments of forgotten games” as told by former football stars for the Alumni Club annual football dinner. (Box 180)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.108, November-December, 1912 - Includes varsity football, basketball, Walter Eckersall’s All-star Eleven, players and coaches, Michigan’s possible return to the Big Nine conference, Michigan and the conference dispute training tables and faculty control over athletics, Walter Camp’s All-American Eleven, program for Intercollegiate Conference Athletic Association games at Purdue, birth announcements, wedding invitations, banquet menus, a song sheet for the States Restaurant Midnight Vaudeville and Cabaret, and a monthly report form for the Department of Physical Culture. (Box 181)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.109, December, 1912-February, 1913 - Includes varsity track, swimming, basketball, new football coaches, football receipts, University of Michigan and the Big Nine Conference question, honorary athletic fraternity Sigma Delta Psi founded, new football rules, intercollegiate chess tournament, fencing, wrestling, golf, “rackets,” Olympian James Thorpe and professionalism, and Thomas Goodspeed retires. Also contains programs for swimming, track and high school athletic meets, poster for Republican candidate and alum Mark Catlin, wedding invitations, birth announcements, indoor athletic schedules for basketball, swimming, track and gymnastics, and a letter defining amateurism. (Box 181)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.110, March-May, 1913 - Interscholastic high school athletics, varsity track, swimming, basketball, baseball, fencing, wrestling, gymnastics, amateurism v. professionalism, summer baseball and student living expenses, possible formation of the Big Ten, and the question of Michigan and the Western Conference. Also have programs for track and high school athletic meets, wedding invitations, and Tin Whistles banquet menu from Pinehurst, North Carolina. (Box 182)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.111, May-September, 1913 - Coverage of track, the 1913 baseball championship, tennis, interscholastic games, the “Athletic Blue Book” of winners of the “C,” obituary for Mary Ingham, creator of the egg sandwich, golf, Western Conference championship track meet, Chicago International Games, summer track exhibitions, Marshall field to be renamed, football coaches and scientific diet. Contains programs for track and interscholastic meets, wedding invitations, and a flyer for the University of Chicago Spring Festival. (Box 182)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.112, September-October, 1913 - Includes football, dedication and programs of the University of Chicago Athletic Field, “Stagg Day” and tickets and passes, players to wear numbers on the field, swimming requirements at Princeton University, history and popularization of football, biographies of Stagg, and wedding invitations. (Box 183)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.113, October-November, 1918 - Football, players and coaches, the question of Michigan returning to the “Big Nine” Western Conference, deaths related to football, the great stars of Chicago’s football team, and articles calling Stagg the “Father of Coaches.” (Box 183)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.114, November, 1913 - Includes varsity football, Michigan and the Western Conference debates, editorials and gossip, articles on Stagg’s career, Chicago’s Department of Physical Culture’s Dr. Reed’s exercises for men who don’t exercise, the twenty-fifth Anniversary of the 1888 Yale Football Team, invitations to weddings and to the Chicago Alumni Club annual football dinner. (Box 184)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.115, November, 1913 - Contains varsity football, recounts and diagrams of games, possible renaming of the athletic field to “Stagg Field, ticket-scalpers, wrestling, Chicago wins the conference title, and Knute Rockne of Notre Dame. Also have programs for the Chicago Alumni football dinner, telegrams, wedding invitations, and a program for the University of Chicago and the University of Wisconsin Glee and Mandolin Club joint concert. (Box 184)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.116, November-December, 1913 - Includes varsity football conference championship, “Big Nine” coaches, numbered uniforms for athletes, indoor track and basketball, possible games between the Ivy Leagues and the West, coaching reforms, proposed ban on professional coaching, baseball reforms, and the Tin Whistle Golf Tournament. Also contains alumni announcement of Mr. Noyes donation of the women’s gymnasium, and a program and constitution of the Pinehurst country club and golf tournament. (Box 185)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.117, January-March, 1914 - Pinehurst golf tournament, basketball, 1914 football schedules, varsity track, swimming, Ivy League football to play the West, and predictions about Michigan and the Western Conference. Stagg’s twenty-two suggestions for changes in football, summer baseball, coaches banned from sidelines, numbers for players, scarlet fever scare in athletics, “Big Nine” golf, and an article on “why football men succeed in politics. Scrapbook also includes programs for track and swimming meets, and wedding invitations. (Box 185)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.118, March-May, 1914 - Includes varsity track, swimming, football, gymnastics, wrestling, fencing, summer baseball, physician declares brown-eyed athletes superior, handwritten record of the Chicago two-mile relay team, Chicago baseball team plays Chinese University of Hawaii, articles on how Stagg believes the “stage” is detrimental to athletics, tennis, “bleacher etiquette and athletic courtesy,” and an Olympic-style parade for the Big Nine Athletic Carnival. Also contains programs for intercollegiate track, swimming, wrestling, fencing, and gymnastic meets, wedding invitations, and a report on the Illinois-Wisconsin track meet by M. Satton. (Box 186)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.119, May-August, 1914 - Articles on track, high school athletics, Missouri Valley Conference track meet, Stanford track, possible spring football practice, baseball, and tennis. The congress of the International Amateur Athletic Federation of European Countries defines and adopts the Olympic code, golf, articles on training “touchdown” stars, Michigan’s six new football plays, automatic exercise machine, and the possible realignment of the “Big Nine.” Also contains, wedding invitations, advertisement for the Conference track meet and dinner, programs for the University of Pennsylvania Relay Races, first annual Chicago Suburban High School Conference track meet, relays, intercollegiate track, interscholastic tournaments, Missouri Valley Conference, tennis, and vaudeville. (Box 186)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.120, September-October, 1914 - Coverage of football, breakdown of major mid-western teams, Stagg rides a motorcycle during practice, diagrams of games, rules enforcing amateurism, Athletic Association report for the spring, 1914 receipts, loans and finances, “Chicago’s Game” ticket holder, football program sheet, wedding invitations, and football programs and line-ups. (Box 187)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.121, October-November, 1914 - Includes varsity football, western schools play Ivy League, Stagg uses Purdue’s tactics to prepare for the game, player line-ups and diagrams of games, ticket scalpers, football player uses President Taft’s “diet” to loose weight, cross-country running, Illinois homecoming, swim meet dates set, proposed foot ball game to raise money for Belgian refugees, telegrams, football programs, and card from Alumni club about football dinner (Box 187)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.122, November, 1914 (1 Oversize Folder see Box 338) - Contains football, players and coaches, Yale-Harvard bowl, athletic field remained ‘Stagg field,” movies of games are used, golf, first Chinese football player at Chicago, basketball, swimming, football scorecard, poster advertising football dinner (oversize), Yearly Buffoon with a war extra, and a football card with the player line-up. (Box 188)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.123, November, 1914-January, 1915 - Includes varsity basketball, football, swimming, cross-country running, water basketball, baseball, women’s field hockey, and the debate over playing more than two sports (two-sport rule). Also contains Big Nine organization of coaches, athletic association’s treasurer’s report on athletic receipts, defining amateurism, professional v. non-competing amateurs, gymnastics, fencing, swim meet programs, and a handwritten track line-up sheet for a meet. (Box 188)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.124,January-March, 1915 - Coverage of varsity basketball, track, baseball, changes in football, assigning numbers to athletes, first Asian varsity athlete, state of athletics at Minnesota, two-sport rule, swimming, hypnotism to be used for baseball, and the Big Nine conference track meet. Also contains baseball scorecards, programs for swimming, track, conference meets, and high school athletics, and an invitation to Rules Committee dinner. (Box 189)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.125, March-May, 1915 - Includes varsity baseball, track, wrestling, gymnastics, relay races, University of Chicago to play baseball in Japan, indoor athletic schedules, track and championship programs, wedding invitations, programs for relay races, and an announcement for the laying of the first brick of Ida Noyes Hall. (Box 189)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.126, May-July, 1915 - Includes track, baseball, tennis, football receipts, interscholastic high school athletics, swimming, an article on Mayor of Chicago and former Maroon football Player, Bill Thompson, walking for exercise, Eskimo football teams, the International Olympic Committee and the Far Eastern Amateur Athletics. Also contains wedding invitations, University of Chicago class reunion advertisements, and programs for track championships and Intercollegiate Conference Athletic Association meets. (Box 190)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.127, August-October, 1915 - Contains varsity track, tennis, West Coast athletic conference, golf, and University of Chicago baseball in Japan, football, Amos Alonzo Stagg Jr. and Ruth Stagg. Also contains wedding invitations, photos, a souvenir menu, song sheets, Olympic Club temporary membership cards, and the daily program for the Panama-Pacific International Exposition in San Francisco. (Box 190)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No.128, October, 1915 - Covers football, players and coaches, James Thorpe to coach at the University of Indiana, Japanese play Chicago in baseball, accounts of the baseball trip in Japan, recounts of football games, and cross-country running. Also contains football and Intercollegiate Conference Athletic Association programs. (Box 191)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 129, October-November, 1915 - Includes football, summer baseball debate, accounts of Japanese baseball games with the University of Chicago, football programs, membership and temporary guest cards, song sheets, toasts to Stagg, and a speech given to the Chicago Alumni Association. (Box 191)
    - Athletic Scrapbook No. 130, November-December, 1915 - Contains varsity football and players, cross-country running, ticket scalping, basketball, professionalism and college athletics, track, and possible abolishment of collegiate baseball. Also contains postcards, a football program, and an invitation to the Western Conference Alumni Association Smoker. (Box 192)